A Guide to the James Branch Cabell Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #5618-a, -b, and -c
James Branch Cabell Collection 1897-1955
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
5618-a, -c, and -d
ca. 1000 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 1971 July
Container List
- Manuscripts
  - "Above Paradise", n.d.; TMs, 11 p. (Box Box 1)
    [w/autograph corrections.]
  - "The Appeal to Posterity", 1922 Feb; TMs, 7 p. (Box Box 1)
  - "Around Lichfield", TMs, 23 p. (Box Box 1)
    [Foreword to an anthology, w/autograph corrections.]
  - "Art, Beauty, and Balderdash", TMs, 9 p. (Box Box 1)
  - "Art, Beauty, and Balderdash", TMsS, 6 p. (Box Box 1)
  - "The Arts in Gaza", n.d.; TMs, 8 p. (Box Box 1)
    [Review of
    Poe's Richmond
    by Agnes Bondurant, w/autograph corrections.]
  - First draft of As I Remember It, [1955]; TMs, 300 p. (Box Box 1)
  - Printer's copy of As I Remember It, [1955]; TMs, ca. 220 p. (Box Box 1)
  - Discarded pages from As I Remember It, [1955]; TMs, ca. 100 p. (Box Box 1)
  - "Between Worlds", n.d.; TMsS, 8 p. (Box Box 1)
  - Bibliography of Cabell writings, 1949 Jul 3; TMs, 68 p. (Box Box 1)
  - "Biography of the Life of Manuel", n.d.; TMs, ca. 200 p. (Box Box 1)
    [20 author's notes, w/autograph corrections.]
  - "The Bright Bees of Toupan", n.d.; TMs, 10 p. (Box Box 2)
  - Review of A Certain Measure by Ellen Glasgow, n.d.; TMs, 4 p. (Box Box 2)
  - "The Chivalry of Ellen Glasgow", n.d.; AMs, 4 p. (Box Box 2)
  - "The Chivalry of Ellen Glasgow", n.d.; TMsS, 11 p. (Box Box 2)
  - "The Comedian", n.d.; TMs, 5 p. (Box Box 2)
  - "Concerning David Jogram", 1911 Jan; TMs, 12 p. (Box Box 2)
    [w/autographcorrections]
  - Printer's copy of "Concerning David Jogram", n.d.; TMs, 13 p. (Box Box 2)
  - "The Contentment of Saraide", n.d.; TMs, 12 p. (Box Box 2)
  - "Coth at Portusa", n.d.; TMs, 13 p. (Box Box 2)
  - Printer's copy of epilogue of The Cream of the Jest, n.d.; TMs, 5 p. (Box Box 2)
  - First draft of preface to The Devil's Own Dear Son, 1948 Nov 27; TMsS, 14 p. (Box Box 2)
  - Second draft of The Devil's Own Dear Son, [1949]; TMs, 161 p. (Box Box 2)
  - "Dizain of the Doomed", n.d.; TMsS, 9 p. (Box Box 2)
  - "Ellen Glasgow", n.d.; TMs, 4 p. (Box Box 2)
  - "Exit", n.d.; TMs, 7 p. (Box Box 2)
  - ["Factual Fiction"] re: The First Gentleman of America, [1942]; TMs, 3 p. (Box Box 2)
  - First draft of Figures of Earth, in 2 parts, [1920]; TMsS, AMs, TMs (carbon), ca. 150 p. (Box Box 2)
  - First draft of The First Gentleman of America, [1942]; TMs, ca. 220 p. (Box Box 2)
  - Notes and discarded passages from The First Gentleman of America, [1942]; TMs, AMs, 45 p. (Box Box 2)
    [w/autograph corrections]
  - "Assisting Data" for The First Gentleman of America, 1941; TMs (Box Box 2)
    [Gathered by E.W. Lawson. ]
  - "The Fourth Mrs. Paterson," review of Never Ask the End by Isabel Paterson, TMsS, 5 p. (Box Box 2)
  - "The Fourth Mrs. Paterson", n.d.; TMs, 5 p. (Box Box 2)
    [Clean copy.]
  - First draft of Hamlet Had an Uncle, 1939 Jul; TMs, ca. 200 p. (Box Box 3)
    [In a binder, w/autograph corrections]
  - Second version of Hamlet Had an Uncle, 1939 Jul; TMs, ca. 150 p. (Box Box 3)
    [w/autograph corrections and insertions.]
  - First draft of The High Place, [1923]; AMs, 39 p. (Box Box 3)
    [w/note by author: "The only first draft of any book by me in existence."]
  - The High Place, [1923]; TMs, ca. 150 p. (Box Box 3)
  - Early draft of part of "Homage of Col. Esmond", TMs, 6 p. (Box Box 3)
  - "Homage to Col. Esmond", TMs, 7 p. (Box Box 3)
  - First draft of I Go to My Father [The Devil's Own Dear Son], [1949]; TMs, ca. 160 p. (Box Box 3)
  - Notes for I Go to My Father, [1949]; AMs, 11 p. (Box Box 3)
  - "In the Sylvan's House", n.d.; TMs, 14 p. (Box Box 3)
  - "The Jewel Merchants", [1921]; TMsS, 28 p. (Box Box 3)
    [carbon, w/autograph corrections.]
  - Jurgen, Chapters XXI-L, from first edition, [1918]; TMs, 194 p. (Box Box 3)
  - First draft of The King Was in His Counting House, [1938]; TMs, AMs, ca. 170 p. (Box Box 4)
  - Second version of The King Was in His Counting House, [1938]; TMs, 215 p. (Box Box 4)
  - Parts for first versions of Ladies and Gentleman, [1934]; TMs, 49 p. (Box Box 5)
  - Second version of Ladies and Gentleman, [1934]; TMs, 103 p. (Box Box 5)
    [w/autograph corrections, and TMs (carbon).]
  - "Last Cry of Romance," review of Barren Ground by Ellen Glasgow, 1925 Apr; TMsS, 4 p. (Box Box 5)
  - Data for Let Me Lie, [1946]; TMs, 27 p.; 12 clippings (Box Box 5)
  - First drafts of Let Me Lie, [1946]; TMs, AMs, 200 p. (Box Box 5)
  - Let Me Lie, [1946]; TMs, 300 p. (Box Box 5)
    [w/ covering 4 pp. typed memo from Marjorie May, editor at Farrar's, to James Branch Cabell, w/autograph corrections.]
  - First draft of "The Lineage of Lichfield", 1921 Aug; TMs, AMs, 15 p. (Box Box 6)
  - "The Lineage of Lichfield," "Epistle Dedicatory," later version, [1921]; TMs, 13 p. (Box Box 6)
    [w/3 printer's sheets, w/autograph corrections.]
  - "A Little More About Eve," preface to Something About Eve, [1928]; TMs, 5 p. (Box Box 6)
    [w/autograph corrections and additions.]
  - Later version of "A Little More About Eve", [1928]; TMs, 6 p. (Box Box 6)
    [carbon]
  - Printer's copy of "A Little More About Eve", 1928 Oct; TMs, 9 p. (Box Box 6)
  - "Maid of Honor", n.d.; TMs, 10 p. (Box Box 6)
  - Later version of "Maid of Honor", n.d.; TMs, 17 p. (Box Box 6)
  - "The Marriage of Bel-Imperia", n.d.; TMs, 12 p. (Box Box 6)
  - "The Mathematics of Gonfal", n.d.; TMs, 16 p. (Box Box 6)
  - "Minus One-Third", n.d.; TMs, 3 p. (Box Box 6)
  - First draft of "The Music From Behind the Moon", [1926]; TMs, 21 p. (Box Box 6)
  - First Version of The Nightmare Has Triplets, n.d.; TMs, 62 p. (Box Box 6)
  - "A Note as to Ettarre," preface to The Witch-Woman, [1948]; TMs, 11 p. (Box Box 6)
  - "A Note for the Intending Reader." preface to The House of Lost Identity by Donald Corley, 1927 Feb 22; TMsS, 2 p. (Box Box 6)
    [carbons. w/autograph corrections.]
  - "A Note on Frances Newman", 1929 Aug 11; TMs, 7 p. (Box Box 6)
  - "A Note on Lichfield," preface to illustrated edition of The Cream of the Jest, 1927 Jan; TMs, 3 p. (Box Box 6)
  - "A Note Upon Branch Cabell", n.d.; TMs, 3 p. (Box Box 6)
  - Printer's copy of "A Note Upon Cabellian Harmonics", 1924 Jan; TMs, 8 p. (Box Box 6)
  - "Of Horses", 1951 May 24; TMs, 23 p. (Box Box 6)
  - "Of Messer Marco Polo, Sixteen years Old", n.d.; TMs, 4 p. (Box Box 6)
  - "On Second Thought," from Brussel's Bibliography of Cabell, [1932]; AMs, 2 p. (Box Box 6)
  - First typed version of "On Second Thought", [1932]; TMs, 3 p. (Box Box 6)
  - Second typed version of "On [upon] Second Thought", [1932]; TMs, 4 p. (Box Box 6)
  - "Once More, the Immortals," review of Fantastica by Robert Nichols, 1923 Sep; TMs, 4 p. (Box Box 6)
  - "One Face and Another," review of The Face of the World by Johan Bojer, 1919 Sep; TMsS, 5 p. (Box Box 6)
  - First version of "Porcelain Cups", n.d.; TMsS, 19 p. (Box Box 6)
  - "Portrait of the Artist: Full Lenth," review of works of George Moore, 1923 Oct; TMs, 6 p. (Box Box 6)
  - "Preface to the Past", [1936]; TMs, 10 p. (Box Box 6)
  - First draft of Quiet, Please, [1952]; TMs, 37 p. (Box Box 6)
  - Quiet, Please and associated data, [1952]; TMs, TMs (carbon), 185 p. (Box Box 6)
  - "Realism", [1935]; TMs, 2 p. (Box Box 6)
    [w/ clipping of printed version and clipping of H. L. Mencken's reply; w/autograph corrections.]
  - "The Revival of a Classic," review of Mother Goose, 1897; TMsS, 4 p. (Box Box 6)
  - First draft of Part I of The St. Johns, [1943]; TMs, TMs (carbon), 260 p. (Box Box 7)
    [w/autograph corrections & additions.]
  - First draft of Part II of The St. Johns, [1943]; TMs, TMS (carbon), 240 p. (Box Box 7)
  - Second draft of The St. Johns, [1943]; TMs, TMs (carbon), 260 p. (Box Box 7)
  - Printer's copy of The St. Johns, [1943]; TMsS, 300 p. (Box Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous data for The St. Johns, [1943]; TMs, AMs, ca. 100 p. (Box Box 8)
  - First draft by A.J. Hanna for The St. Johns, [1943]; TMs, ca. 160 p. (Box Box 8)
  - "The Scope of the Novel", n.d.; TMs, 5 p. (Box Box 8)
  - First version of The Silver Stallion, [1925]; TMs, TMs (carbon), ca. 200 p. (Box Box 8)
  - Early drafts of Smire, [1937]; TMs, AMs, ca. 200 p. (Box Box 8)
  - First version of Smire, [1937]; TMs, 215 p. (Box Box 8)
  - First draft of Smirt, [1934]; TMs, AMs, ca. 125 p. (Box Box 8)
  - Second version of Smirt, [1934]; TMs, 182 p. (Box Box 9)
  - First draft of Smith, [1935]; TMs, ca. 230 p. (Box Box 9)
  - Second draft of Smith, [1935]; TMs, ca. 110 p. (Box Box 9)
  - "Some Objections to Branch Cabell", n.d.; TMsS, 3 p. (Box Box 9)
  - First draft of Some of Us, [1930]; TMs, 77 p. (Box Box 9)
    [w/clippings tipped in; w/autograph corrections and additions.]
  - First draft of Something About Eve, [1927]; TMs, ca. 75 p. (Box Box 9)
  - Discarded pages from Something About Eve, [1927]; TMs, AMs, ca. 200 p. (Box Box 9)
  - Second draft of Something about Eve, 2 v., [1927]; TMs, ca. 170 p. (Box Box 9)
  - "Sonnets from Antan", n.d.; AMsS, 10 p. (Box Box 10)
  - First drafts of Special Delivery, [1933]; TMs, AMs, ca. 130 p. (Box Box 10)
  - First version of Straws and Prayer Books, 2 v., [1924]; TMs, ca. 230 p. (Box Box 10)
    [w/autograph corrections & note.]
  - First version of Taboo, 1920 Dec; TMs, 19 p. (Box Box 10)
  - There Were Two Pirates, [1946]; TMs, 72 p. (Box Box 10)
  - First drafts of These Restless Heads, [1932]; TMsS, TMs (carbon) and AMs, ca. 300 p. (Box Box 10)
  - Printer's copy of These Restless Heads, 1931 Jul; TMs, 150 p. (Box Box 11)
  - "The Thin Queen of Elfhame", n.d.; TMs, 7 p. (Box Box 11)
  - "Townsend of Lichfield", [1929]; TMsS, AMs, 12 p. (Box Box 11)
    [w/autograph corrections on TMsS.]
  - Unrevised carbon of "Townsend of Lichfield", [1929]; TMs (carbon), 10 p. (Box Box 11)
  - Printer's copy of "Townsend of Lichfield", 1929 Apr 14; TMs, 24 p. (Box Box 11)
  - "Turtle-Meat and Broomsticks," review of From a Southern Porch by Dorothy Scarborough, 1919 Nov; TMs, 14 p. (Box Box 11)
  - Clean copy of "Turtle-Meat and Broomsticks", 1919 Nov; TMs, 4 p. (Box Box 11)
  - First version of "The Water of Airdra", [1935]; TMs, 10 p. (Box Box 11)
    [became "Book of Elair" in
    Smith
    w/autograph corrections.]
  - Second version of "The Water of Airdra", [1935]; TMs, 13 p. (Box Box 11)
  - Draft of "The Way of Ecben", [1929]; AMs, 3 p. (Box Box 11)
  - First draft of Part I of "The Way of Ecben", [1929]; TMs, 22 p. (Box Box 11)
  - Later version of "The Way of Ecben", [1929]; TMs, 69 p. (Box Box 11)
  - First version of "The Ways of Women", n.d.; Photostat of TMs, 7 p. (Box Box 11)
  - First version of first part of "The White Robe", [1928]; TMs, 8 p. (Box Box 11)
  - First draft of "The White Robe", [1928]; TMs, 32 p. (Box Box 11)
    [Inscribed to Frances Newman; w/autograph corrections.]
  - Printer's copy of "The White Robe", [1928]; TMs, 32 p. (Box Box 11)
  - "The Witch-Woman", [1948]; TMs, 8 p. (Box Box 11)
  - "A Word to My Followers", n.d.; TMs, 4 p. (Box Box 11)
- Photographs and prints
  - Cabell Room, Valentine Museum, Richmond, Virginia, Picture postcard (Box Box 11)
  - Exhibit of Cabell material at [ University of Florida], n.d.; Photo (Box Box 11)
  - 43 illustrations by Frank C. Papé; for books by James Branch Cabell, n.d.; Engravings (Box Box 11)
- Miscellaneous
  - Notes and parts of essays, 13 unidentified pages, AMs, TMs (Box Box 11)
  - Pamphlets
    - "Bibliographic Check List of the Works of James Branch Cabell" by Merle Johnson, 1921; Pamphlet, 28 p. (Box Box 11)
      [signed by author.]
    - Two copies of "James Branch Cabell" by H. L. Mencken, 1928; Pamphlet, 33 p. (Box Box 11)
    - "Joseph Hergesheimer, an Essay in Interpretation" by James Branch Cabell, 1921; Pamphlet, 27 p. (Box Box 11)
    - 2 copies of "The Nightmare Has Triplets, An Author's Notes on Smire " by James Branch Cabell, 1937; Pamphlet, 14 p. (Box Box 11)
    - "Of Ellen Glasgow, an Inscribed Portrait" by James Branch Cabell and Ellen Glasgow, 1938; Pamphlet, 16 p. (Box Box 11)
  - Proofs
    - The First Gentleman of America, [1942]; Corrected gallery proofs, 71 strips (Box Box 11)
    - Hamlet Had an Uncle, [1940]; Corrected galley proofs, 70 strips (Box Box 11)
    - "The Jewel Merchants", [1921]; Corrected page proofs, 63 pp. (Box Box 11)
    - Jurgen, Penguin Edition, n.d.; Page proofs, 71 strips (Box Box 12)
    - "A Little More About Eve", [1928]; Corrected galley proofs, 4 strips (Box Box 12)
    - "A Note for the Intending Reader", [1927]; Corrected page proofs, 3 p. (Box Box 12)
    - Quiet, Please, [1952]; Corrected page proofs, 105 p. (Box Box 12)
    - 2 groups of The St. Johns, [1943]; Corrected galley proofs, 78 strips (Box Box 12)
    - The St. Johns, [1943]; Corrected page proofs, 317 p. (Box Box 12)
    - The St. Johns p. 1-318, [1943]; Corrected page proofs (Box Box 12)
      [Large paged proof sheets]
    - Illustrations of opening sections of The Silver Stallion, [1925]; Galley proofs, 5 strips (Box Box 12)